｢There was a hungry crow｣
♪ ｢お 腹 空 かせた ｶﾗｽがいた｣
｢who somehow wanted to get some feed｣
♪ ｢なんとか 餌 に ありつきたい｣
｢if only this beak were longer｣
♪ ｢この くちばしが もっと長ければ｣
｢that feed would be a bit closer｣
♪ ｢あの餌が もっと こっちに来れば｣
♪ ～
♪ ～
｢a crow can think｣
｢ｶﾗｽは 考え る ｶﾗｽは考える ｶﾗｽは考える ｶﾗｽは考える｣
｢can think... can think｣
♪ ｢考える 考える｣
Observe, propose a hypothesis, experiment and then consider.
( 斎藤 )観察し 仮 説を立て 実験をし 考察する｡
Lean the way of scientific thought.
科学の考え方を学べ｡
First we start with a ｢Thinking Observation｣
(山本)まずは ｢考える観察｣から｡
If we flick this pen cap with our finger...
ペンのｷｬｯﾌﾟを 指で はじくと →
Look closely.
よく回る｡
Today, we will be observing this.
今日は これを観察してみる｡
Try putting a mark on the cap with a sticker.
ｷｬｯﾌﾟに ｼｰﾙで 印を付けてみる｡
Watch the mark when we flick the cap.
指で はじくと 印が見える｡
Flick it once more.
もう一度 はじく｡
This time we can't see the mark.
今度は 印が見えない｡
And if we spin it once more...
また回すと…｡
We see it.
見えた｡
What's the difference between the time when we can see the mark and when we can't?
見える時と 見えない時 何が ちがうのか｡
Try spinning it some times.
何度か 回してみる｡
We can see it.
見える｡
We can't see it.
見えない｡
Watch carefully the position of our finger when flicking it.
指で はじく位置に 注意してみる｡
Flick it on the side we've put the sticker.
印が付いている方を はじいてみる｡
We can see the mark.
印が 見えた｡
This time flick from the side we haven't put the sticker.
今度は 印が付いていない方を はじく｡
We can't see the mark.
印は 見えない｡
Confirm by placing a mark on the opposite side.
反対側に 別の印を付けて 確認 する｡
Flick on the circle side...
丸の方を はじくと…｡
We can't see anything but the circle.
丸しか 見えない｡
If we flick on the side with the triangle...
三角の方を はじくと…｡
We can't see anything but the triangle.
三角しか 見えない｡
But the circle and triangle and on the same side.
しかし 丸と三角は 同じ面に はってある｡
When we can see the circle, we ought not be able to see the triangle at the same time?
丸が見える時 三角も同時に 見えるはずではないか｡
but...
でも…｡
we can only see the circle.
丸しか 見えない｡
What's going on here?
何が起こっているのか｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
Today our problem uses this balloon.
( 蒼井 )今日は この風船を使った問題です｡
We affix this balloon to this trolley here.
ここにある台車に 風船をつけます｡
When we push this trolley forward...
そして この台車を前におした時 →
What will happen to the balloon?
風船が どうなるかというと…｡
It tilted backwards.
後ろに たおれます｡
You understand this so far, don't you?
ここまでは わかりますよね？
Now, this is the problem.
さて ここからが問題です｡
This time we put a transparent box
今度は この 透明 の箱で →
and push it
風船を すっぽりと おおってしまいます｡
Now, before we push the cart...
そして この台車を 前におした時 →
What will happen to the balloon?
風船は どうなるでしょうか？
1. Like before it will tilt backwards.
１｡ さっきと同じように 後ろに たおれる｡
2. It will do the opposite, and tilt forward.
２｡ ぎゃくに 前に たおれる｡
3. It will remain as it is, and not tilt.
３｡ そのまま たおれない｡
Everyone, think really carefully about it, won't you?
みなさん よ～く 考えておいてくださいね｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
Now the answer to our question earlier.
では 先ほどの答えです｡
Did you think it through properly?
みなさん ちゃ～んと考えましたか？
Now then, let's really try it.
では 実際 に やってみましょう｡
Let's go.
いきますよ｡
What will happen to the balloon. Look really carefully.
風船が どうなるか よ～く見ていてくださいね｡
Did you get it?
わかりましたか？
Let's look at that once more.
もう一度 見てみましょう｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
The answer...
答えは…
But why do you think that happens?
でも どうして そうなるのでしょう？
In things there is a property that tries to remain the same.
ものには その場に とどまろうとする 性質 があります｡
Covering the balloon with a box and pushing the cart...
箱を風船にかぶせて 台車をおした時 →
The air in the box remains in place...
箱の中の空気は その場に とどまろう…｡
From her on we think for ourselves.
ここから先は 自分で考えよう｡
From here on we're thinking crows.
これからは みんなが 考えるｶﾗｽ｡